Guide to the Wyona S. Coleman Papers, 1971-2005 AIS.2000.21
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Wyona S. Coleman Papers
1971-2005
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Coleman, Wyona S.
AIS.2000.21
21.25 Linear Feet (17 boxes)
The Papers of Wyona Coleman document a period of escalating environmental activism. A dedicated environmentalist, Coleman has campaigned on the local, state, and federal levels of government for effective means to protect and to mitigate harm to the environment caused by the acquisition of natural resources and refuse disposal. The bulk of Coleman's papers relate to coal mining and detail her position as a representative of the Sierra Club of Pennsylvania on various committees of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, Department of Environmental Protection (DEP), formerly known as the Department of Environmental Resources (DER). These committees addressed such issues as the impact of coal mining (especially longwall mining), solid waste disposal, and oil and natural gas drilling on the environment. Materials include committee meeting minutes and notes, correspondence, drafts of legislation, evidence of lawsuits resulting from changes in legislation, educational publications, and newspaper clippings.
Biography
Coleman began life as Wyona Smith on March 23, 1932 in Steeleville, Illinois. She earned her Bachelor of Arts degree from Southern Illinois University, Carbondale, Illinois. Coleman joined The Courier of Urbana, Illinois in 1956 and after four years left the paper for a public relations position with the Illinois Geological Survey.
In 1967, Coleman relocated to western Pennsylvania, where she became increasingly involved in the environmental movement. She campaigned to expand the National Wild and Scenic Rivers System in western Pennsylvania. She also participated in the first national Earth Day, April 22, 1970 on the campus of California State College, California, Pennsylvania. During the same year Coleman joined the Brownsville Telegraph as a freelance reporter and editor. In 1972, she contributed to the formation of the Pennsylvania Chapter of the Sierra Club. Coleman became more active on the state level representing the Sierra Club on a number of Commonwealth of Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Resources (DER) committees. She participated on various committees including the Mining Legislative Task Force, Mining and Reclamation Advisory Board, Coal Work Group, and the Bonding Advisory Board. The purpose of the committees was to formulate legislation and regulations in response to the 1977 Surface Mining Control and Reclamation Act (SMCRA), which allowed states greater regulatory control over surface mining.
In 1980, the Pennsylvania DER created the Solid Waste Advisory Committee in response to the growing issue of solid waste disposal. Coleman participated in this committee and played a significant role in the creation of Getting Involved, a DER publication on public participation in the siting of waste facilities. Coleman also participated in a number of supplementary committees such as the Hazardous Waste Facilities Planning Advisory Committee, Hazardous Waste Siting Committee and the Recycling Fund Advisory Committee. In 1981, Governor Thornburgh recognized her participation among others in a "Decade of Service" to the DER proclamation with a ceremony and luncheon.
While serving on the DER committees, Coleman also chaired the Pennsylvania Chapter of the Sierra Club from 1981 to1983 and again from 1985 to 1986. During her terms she established a full-time lobbyist position in Harrisburg for the Pennsylvania Chapter.
As coal companies turned to long-wall mining, the removal of large panels of coal that cause subsidence affecting natural features and man-made structures, Coleman sought to protect citizens' rights in the coalfields of Ohio, West Virginia, and Pennsylvania. She contributed to the organization of the Tri-State Citizens Mining Network in 1994 to create awareness and advocate for the protection of citizens, their rights and the environment. The Network has protested long-wall mining activities, such as those that have undermined Interstate 70, and advocates for victims of subsidence and water loss. In 2000, the Pennsylvania Wildlife Federation awarded her the Gail Rockwood Public Service Award. On the state level, Coleman coordinated Sierra Club Training to develop the next generation of leaders for the environmental movement. From 2000 to 2005 she served as the Mining, Oil, Gas Conservation Issue Chair. Coleman continued to work for environmental rights until her death in 2005.
Scope and Content Notes
The papers of Wyona S. Coleman document the impact of the environmental movement, primarily in western Pennsylvania, on state and federal regulations. Much of the material concerns mitigating the harmful effects of procuring natural resources. In an effort to minimize damage caused by coal mining, groups, such as the Sierra Club, participated with the DER in the drafting and amendment of the Surface Mining Control and Reclamation Act (SMRCA) of 1977. Since Pennsylvania had an established version of this federal mandate (SMCRA, 1945), Coleman and other members lobbied for stricter regulations on the federal SMCRA, especially during the drafting of the "State Window" legislation that allowed states the opportunity to relax their existing rules as long as they were no less strict than the federal legislation.
As the demand for coal increased in the 1990s, Coleman worked with activist groups that focused on longwall mining, which had become the method of choice for mining companies. The collection also includes information on safety regulations imposed on solid waste disposal in Pennsylvania, as well as studies, research materials, and articles on many other environmental topics. The collection is rich in information about how environmental degradation affected the safety of homes and property value, water, and wildlife.
Arrangement
The Coleman papers have been arranged into the following series. Extensive scope notes on each topic are available in the container list.
Series I: Coal Mining
Series II: Solid Waste Disposal
Series III: Oil and Natural Gas Drilling, 1980-1998
Series IV: Longwall Mining
Series V: Research
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Wyona S. Coleman on December 20, 2000, and Phillip Coleman in 2005.
Previous Citation
Wyona S. Coleman Papers, 1971-2005, AIS.2000.21, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh.
Longwall mining -- Pennsylvania; Hazardous waste sites -- Pennsylvania; Environmental policy -- Pennsylvania; Waste disposal sites -- Pennsylvania; Personal papers; Environment; Women; Appalachian Region; Pennsylvania; Greene County (Pa.); Allegheny National Forest (Pa.); Environmentalists -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Women environmentalists -- Pennsylvania; Environmental protection -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny National Forest; Strip mining -- Appalachian Region; Coal mines and mining -- Environmental aspects -- Pennsylvania; Coal mines and mining -- Law and legislation -- Pennsylvania; Coal mines and mining -- Waste disposal -- Pennsylvania; Gas wells -- Environmental aspects -- Pennsylvania; Oil wells -- Environmental aspects -- Pennsylvania; Environmental Law & Policy Center; Pennsylvania. Department of Environmental Protection; Pennsylvania. Department of Environmental Resources; Citizens Coal Council; Coleman, Wyona S.; Environmental Resources Management (ERM) Group; Tri-State Citizens Mining Network; Sierra Club. Pennsylvania Chapter; United States. Surface Mining Control and Reclamation Act of 1977; Sierra Club. Pennsylvania Chapter. Allegheny Group
- Coal Mining, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series documents the transfer of greater powers to the states to regulate coal mining as a result of the Surface Mining Control and Reclamation Act of 1977, SMCRA. This process included the drafting of regulations, hearings, and litigation. In Pennsylvania, regulations were drafted by committees assisted by advisory groups that included a variety of stakeholders. Coleman participated in a number of committees representing the Pennsylvania Chapter of the Sierra Club.
  - Department of Environmental Resources,(DER) Committee Documents, 1977-1987; 1.
    The DER committees were created in response to the passage of the Federal SMCRA of 1977. The act sought to address environmental concerns throughout the mining cycle from site selection to its reclamation. The act created the Office of Surface Mining (OSM) in the Department of the Interior to implement state regulations that complied with SMCRA standards.
    This sub-series contains committee materials collected by Coleman during her participation in the Mining Legislation Ad Hoc Task Force, the subsequent Mining Advisory Committee, Ad Hoc Mining Task Force and the Coal Work Group. The task forces formulated legislation while the work group sought to identify regulations that may have restricted production of Pennsylvania coal. The committees' materials include documents on Section 522, Lands Designated Unsuitable for Mining and the Ad Hoc Task Force's Final Report. The committee materials also include correspondence, a report, and a response document from the Pennsylvania Bureau of Mining and Reclamation concerning the product of the Coal Work Group.
    - Mining Legislation - Ad Hoc Task Force, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
    - Mining Advisory Committee, Ad Hoc Mining Task Force, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Coal Work Group, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - Governmental and Non-Governmental Organization Documents, 1971-1993; 2.
    This sub-series contains governmental, non-governmental, and subject files concerning mining regulation and legislation. The regulations cover a number of areas such as blasting, bonding, and revegetation. Additional files can be found in Series IV: Longwall Mining. Coleman collected these documents in support of her activities with the Commonwealth and the Pennsylvania Chapter of the Sierra Club. The documents were produced by a number of different agencies and organizations including the Office of Surface Mining (OSM), Department of Environmental Resources (DER), The Beleaguered Earth Study Group, the League of Women Voters, various Chapters of the Sierra Club, the Environmental Policy Institute, the National Wildlife Federation and the Natural Resource Defense Council to name a few. Documents include articles, comments, conference materials, correspondence, legislation, newspaper clippings, reports, and testimony.
    - Strip Mining, 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
    - Damage to Roads in Luzerne Township Due to Coal Trucks, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Public Hearing on the Petition of Luzerne Coal Corporation, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Conference on Surface-Mined Land for Recreation, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Strip Mining Legislation, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Drafting Pennsylvania Sierra Club Strip Mining Policy, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Farmland in Knox County, Illinois, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Proposed Regulations, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Citizens' Grievance, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
    - OSM Vacancy Announcement, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Sierra Club National Committee Member Lists, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Pennsylvania State Primacy, 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
    - New Coal Technology, 1978-1987 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - OSM News / Press Releases, 1978-1993 (Box 1, Folder 39-30)
    - Draft Report on Acid Mine Drainage on a Stream, February 07, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Environmental Assessment, Pa. House Bill 106, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Mine Regulation and Enforcement Field Office, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Attempts to Amend SMCRA, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Pennsylvania Proposed Legislation, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - US Congressional Oversight Committees of OSM, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Coal Action Network, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Coal Mining, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Strip Mining Problems in Pennsylvania - Report, March 17, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Notices of Violations, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Two-Acre Exemption and Prime Farm Land Regulation, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - DER Enforcements, 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - State Primacy Regulations, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    - SMCRA Regulation Litigation, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15-21)
    - Confirmation of James R. Harris, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Blasting and Explosives, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Bonding Regulations, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Excess Spoils Regulations, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Revegetation Regulation, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Northcentral Highlands Forum, March 27, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - OSM Rulemaking Calendar, April 23, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Little Kanawha, Burnsville Dam Area and Holly Grove Coal Company, October 01-26, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Watt Draft OSM Regulations, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
    - OSM Reorganization, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Comments on OSM Regulations, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
    - Coal Leasing and Strip Mining Regulations, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Department of Environmental Resources, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Areas Unsuitable for Mining, 1981-1986 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Rural Abandon Mine Program, RAMP, 1981-1988 (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
    - Luzerne Coal Corporation Consent Order and Agreement, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - DER Reponses to Comments on Chapters 86, 87, 89, and 90, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Auger Mining, Experimental Practices, and Topsoil Regulations, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Coal Exploration Regulations, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Chapter 87, Subchapter F, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Abandon Mine / Land and Reclamation, 1983-1992 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
    - Anthracite Coal Mining, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Effluent Limitations Guidelines, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Coal Reclamation Report, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Environmental Policy Institute Contact List, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Citizens Workshop on the Surface Mining Act, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Citizen's Strip-mine Enforcement Workshop, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - OSM Management Action Plan (MAP) Reactions, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Coal Mining and Ground Water Quality Report, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Coal Mining Articles and Reports, 1985-1993 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Strategy Meeting Notice on Mining Issues, February 03, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Surface Mine Reclamation, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Coal Mining Newspaper Clippings, 1986-1993 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - SMCRA 10th Anniversary, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Commonwealth and Federal Legislation, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Pa. Mines and Energy Committee, Ad Hoc Committee on Coal, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Mine Drainage and Surface Mine Reclamation Conference (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Bond Rate Guidelines and Bonding Alternative (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Non-Coal Surface Mining Comment and Response Document (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Abandon Refuse Sites (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Citizens Coal Council (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Acid Mine Drainage, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - House Appropriations Committee, March 17, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Request for Participation in Mineral Extension Study, June 24, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Secretary Babbit Meeting with OSM Employees, July 26, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Solid Waste Disposal, II.
  A number of factors caused the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania to examine its regulations concerning solid waste: the additional use of Pennsylvania landfill sites by other states, the environmental burden of waste disposal, and a lack of regulation to ensure safe disposal of waste. The DER formed committees of the various stakeholders to draft regulations for the safe disposal of solid waste. This included the regulation of facilities siting and of disposing of hazardous waste.
  - Department of Environmental Resources, (DER) Committee Documents, 1981-1993; 1.
    This sub-series contains committee materials collected by Coleman during her participation in the Solid Waste Roundtable, Hazardous Waste Facilities Planning Advisory Committee (HWFPAC), the Solid Waste Advisory Committee (SWAC), the Hazardous Waste Siting Committee (HWSC), and the Recycling Fund Advisory Committee (RFAC). The committees cooperated to recommend to the Department of Environmental Protection regulations to implement a Pennsylvania Hazardous Waste Facilities Plan. The creation of the Pennsylvania Hazardous Waste Facilities Plan was mandated by the Solid Waste Management Act to regulate hazardous waste and plan for the future. HWFPAC and SWAC consisted of a variety of stakeholders including representatives from a waste treatment facility, a waste generator, local governments, environmentalists and academic scientists. The files consist of committee agendas, minutes, correspondence, and supporting materials. The HWFPAC files contain a plan edited by Coleman. The HWSC files contain information on the development of a citizen primer, Getting Involved, concerning public participation in the siting of waste facilities. RFAC, part of SWAC, advised the state on the expenditure of funds generated from fees assessed on the dumping of waste to benefit recycling programs.
    - Solid Waste Management Roundtable, 1981-1983 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Hazardous Waste Facilities Planning Advisory Committee, 1981-1983 (Box 4, Folder 14-18)
    - Solid Waste Advisory Committee (SWAC), 1984-1993 (Box 4, Folder 19-28)
    - Hazardous Waste Siting Committee, 1985-1993 (Box 4, Folder 29-32)
    - Hazardous Waste Siting Committee, 1985-1993 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - DER Review of Advisory Groups, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Recycling Fund Advisory Committee, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Governmental and Non-Governmental Documents, 1978-1993; 2.
    This sub-series contains documents in support of Coleman's participation with the DER Solid Waste committees and the Pennsylvania Chapter of the Sierra Club. These files include documents from other stakeholders, and those not directly attributable to one of the DER Committees. The documents were produced by a number of different agencies and organizations including the Environmental Resources Management (ERM) Group, the League of Women Voters, and the Sierra Club. The files consist of various documents including articles, comments, conference materials, correspondence, legislation, newspaper clippings, reports, and testimony collected by Coleman.
    - Citizens' grievances - hazardous waste, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Hazardous and toxic waste, 1979-1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Pa. House Bill 1840 hazardous waste siting, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
    - Hazardous waste siting comments, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 9-12)
    - Hazardous waste newspaper clippings, 1980-1986 (Box 5, Folder 13-15)
    - Franklin Township and Fayette County vs. DER and Elwin Farms, Inc., December 02, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Hazardous waste statements, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
    - Hazardous waste siting criteria statements, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
    - Hazardous waste siting - proposed rulemaking draft, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Solid waste disposal articles, 1984-1987 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Proposed hazardous waste siting criteria comments, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 23-24)
    - National Small Quantity Hazardous Waste Generator Survey, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Proposed ground water quality protection, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Solid waste newspaper clippings, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Clippings/Articles (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Conference information, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Legislation, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Proposed incinerator ash policies, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Incineration of Biomedical Waste (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Small quantity generators program development options, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Permit -By-Rule Facilities report, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Judging Governor's Waste Minimization Award, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Solid waste legislation from State Senator David J. Brightbill, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Oil and Natural Gas Drilling, 1980-1998; III.
  This series focuses on the environmental effects of oil and natural gas drilling predominately in western Pennsylvania. The documents include correspondence and materials from environmental organizations such as the Sierra Club and the National Citizen's Network as well as newspaper clippings.
  - Citizens' Guide to Oil and Gas Leasing, circa 1980 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Citizens' Advisory Council report on regulations, April 07, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Assessment of oil and gas management programs, 1981-1992 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Oil and Gas Act Pennsylvania SB 402, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Water Contamination, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Allegheny National Forest drilling, 1986-1992 (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
  - Pennsylvania Code Chapters 78, 79, and 97, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Pa. Air and Water Pollution Committee, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Regulations - comments and correspondence, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Oil and Gas Act of 1984, amendments to Act 223, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - National Citizen's Network, 1988-1992 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
  - DER comment and response document, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Oil and gas regulations, 1989-1991 (Box 6, Folder 15-16)
  - Oil and gas waste regulation, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Oil and gas wells - newspaper clippings, 1992, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - National Fuel proposed pipelines, February 17, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Orphan Well Plugging Fund Report, January 1998 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Longwall Mining, IV.
  The series deals primarily with the efforts of environmental groups to limit and control damage caused by longwall mining in Pennsylvania. Longwall mining is an efficient form of underground mining in which a cutting machine removes coal from a seam in large blocks or "panels". As the machine advances, leaving a gap, support structures are removed and the roof of the mine collapses. The resulting subsidence can have a severe impact on homeowners, leading to fissures and bumps in roads, cracked foundations and walls, broken pipes, or permanent loss of well water. Acid mine drainage and disrupted water sources can also harm local ecosystems.
  Coleman worked with groups such as the Sierra Club, the Tri State Citizens Mining Network, and the Citizen's Coal Council to amend state and federal mining regulation and on enforcement of these laws. Most materials in this series reflect the environmentalists' perspective, but Coleman also collected information and articles from coal companies and from local miners, who feared for the security of their jobs.
  This series has been arranged into five subseries: SMCRA, BMSLCA, Court Cases and Other Legal Issues, Bonding, and Groups.
  - SMCRA- State and Federal, 1.